2000年，俄罗斯一发火箭从哈萨克斯坦升空
In the year 2000, a Russian rocket launched from Kazakhstan
将国际空间站的早期组件送入近地轨道
carrying one of the first pieces of the International Space Station into orbit.
尽管这看上去是一次寻常的火箭发射
Although this may look like a normal rocket launch,
但火箭的一侧竟然印着一个巨大的必胜客logo
on the side of the rocket was a giant Pizza Hut logo.
这是广告战的一部分，必胜客花了一百万美元
This was part of an ad campaign where Pizza Hut paid 1 million dollars for Russian cosmonauts
让俄罗斯宇航员在太空吃披萨，还把自家logo印在火箭上
to eat their Pizza in space and to have their logo displayed on the side of the rocket.
但为何这种广告不常出现在火箭上呢？
But why don’t we see ads on the side of rockets more often?
本期视频我们将了解太空飞行中不同寻常的广告史
In this video, we’re going to look at the unusual history of advertisement in space-flight.
我们还将了解为何太空中不常出现广告
We’re also going to look at why it’s not common
以及未来低成本火箭将如何改变这个现状
and how the future of low cost rockets might change that.
在现代的网络、电视世界，广告随处可见
In the modern world of internet and television, advertisements are everywhere:
体育赛事、旅游景点、电影、各种交通工具上
sporting events, tourist attractions, movies, transportation.
只要是能吸引人们注意的地方往往都会有广告
Anything that attracts a lot of attention will also attract advertisement.
2019年的超级碗有一亿人观看
The 2019 Super Bowl was watched by 100 million people,
当时30秒的广告就要花大约五百万美元
making the price for a 30 second commercial around 5 million dollars.
太空发射活动也不是没有这么多观众
But spaceflight is no stranger to large audiences.
1969年人类第一次登月，有了破纪录的六亿人观看
The first Moon landing in 1969 was watched by a record breaking 600 million people
第一发重型猎鹰发射也有上百万人观看在线直播
and the first Falcon Heavy test flight was viewed by millions of people online.
尽管太空发射也能有全世界的关注，但当中却很少发现广告的身影
Despite the worldwide attention, advertisements never found their way to these important spaceflight events.
因为NASA是政府机构，在广告方面有严格政策限制
Due to NASA being a government agency, it has a restrictive policy
其中就包括禁止宇航员和其它雇员接商业广告推广
which stops astronauts and other employees from endorsing products.
比如从航天飞机计划开始的时候
Since the beginning of the Space Shuttle program,
NASA就一直在给空间站送M&M豆吃
NASA has been sending M&M’s up to the Space Station for astronauts to eat.
但为了避免广告嫌疑
However, instead of referring to them as M&M’s,
宇航员只能叫它们“巧克力糖衣豆”
astronauts have to call them ‘candy-coated chocolates’.
一些科技机构估算过，NASA如果打广告可以赚大约一亿美元的经费
The Science and Technology Institute estimated that NASA could make around 100 million dollars in revenue
if they agreed to do a sponsorship and advertisement deal.
但这对于太空工程来说还是显得杯水车薪
However, this is an insignificant amount when it comes to doing business in space.
然而俄罗斯那边则对广告持更开放的态度
The Russian’s on the other hand are far more open to the idea of advertisements.
一名俄罗斯宇航员就曾在太空打过高尔夫
A Russian Cosmonaut famously hit a golf ball into orbit
来为加拿大高尔夫公司的赞助打广告
as part of a paid sponsorship for a Canadian golf company.
在1996年，俄罗斯宇航员把一个巨型百事可乐罐挂在和平号空间站上
In 1996, Russian cosmonauts took a giant Pepsi can into space to float outside the Mir Space Station
以此作为百事可乐广告战的一部分，并成为航天史上首个商业广告
as part of Pepsi’s campaign to make the first commercial in space.
但这和必胜客的计划相比就显得图样了
This is nothing compared to what Pizza Hut were planning.
在2000年，必胜客打算使用高能激光把他们的logo投影到月球表面上
In 2000, they were looking at the idea of projecting their logo onto the surface of the Moon
using high powered lasers.
但在和物理学家讨论过这个想法之后
After discussing the idea with physicists,
他们意识到这个主意的能量需求和精度需求是几乎不可能实现的
they realised that the enormous amount of power and accuracy required to pull this off would be almost impossible
可能要花上亿美元来开发技术
and it would require hundreds of millions of dollars to develop.
于是必胜客想出了把新logo印在俄罗斯质子号火箭身上的替代办法
Instead, Pizza Hut settled with the idea of displaying their new logo on the side of a Russian Proton rocket.
除了这个夸张的广告战之外
Apart from this ambitious advertising campaign,
多数火箭公司还没有向全球赞助商们敞开大门
rocket companies have yet to open their doors to the world of sponsorships.
但随着私人航天公司跻身火箭发射市场，这样的情形将有所改变
But with the new wave of private companies getting into the spaceflight industry, this could change.
像太空叉和火箭实验室这样的公司会极大削减火箭发射开销
Companies like SpaceX and Rocket Lab have drastically cut the cost of launching rockets.
同时又有越来越受欢迎的发射直播的观众
And with the online viewership of these launches growing in popularity,
我们也将能看到各种赞助商们出现在火箭身上，不管我们喜不喜欢
we could start to see sponsored liveries appearing on rockets, whether we like it or not.
所以虽然全球的广告商暂时还没在火箭上打广告
So although the world of advertising has yet to make it’s way into spaceflight,
我们也只能希望将来登陆火星的火箭别是百事可乐赞助的吧
we can only hope that the first step onto Mars isn’t sponsored by Pepsi.
感谢Primal Space的帮助每个视频撰写文稿查找资料的赞助者
Thank you to the Primal Space patrons who helped to write and research each video
如果你想赞助Primal Space频道并加入我们专有Discord群
If you'd like to contribute Primal Space and join our exclusive Discord
请访问patreon.com/primalspace
please visit patreon.com/primalspace
满100名赞助者后会抽三位赠送坎巴拉太空计划
where we will be giving away 3 copies of Kerbal Space Program once we reach 100 patrons
所以记得关注，方便我们讨论、学习所有和太空有关的知识
So make sure you've subscribed, so you can join the discussion as we continue to learn more about all things space
非常感谢您的观看，我们下期视频见
Thank you very much for watching, and I'll see you in the next video